Register of the Richard A. Stratton papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Richard A. Stratton papers
1946-2015
1952-1990
75044
Hoover Institution Archives
26 manuscript boxes, 3 videocassette boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 audio cassette box, 1 card file box, 4 motion picture film reels, 1 oversize tube (21.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoirs, speeches and writings, interview transcripts, memoranda, conference proceedings, flight logs, military records, personal documents, printed matter, and audiovisual material relating to American prisoners of war and persons missing in action during the Vietnam War, and to the treatment of released prisoners in North Vietnam. Includes some papers of Alice M. Stratton, deputy assistant secretary of the Navy for forces support and family, and wife of Richard A. Stratton.
Stratton, Richard A., 1931-
Stratton, Alice M.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual or digital material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975, with increments received in 1978, 1993, 2013, and 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Maerose J. Evans papers, Hoover Institution Archives
National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia miscellany, Hoover Institution Archives
Paul B. Ryan papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Shirley Mae Stark papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Sybil Bailey Stockdale papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Juliene Williams papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Chronology
1931 October 14 Born, Quincy, Massachusetts
1947-1948 Enlisted in Massachusetts National Guard Assigned Private in the 211th Calvary Reconnaissance Squadron
1952-1954 Attended Oblate College
1955 Bachelor of Arts, History and Government, Georgetown University Enlisted in Navy as naval aviation cadet
1957 Designated Naval Aviator
1958-1962 Joined Carrier Air Group Nine, Attack Squadron Ninety-four aboard USS Ranger; deployed to Western Pacific Commissioned Lieutenant
1959 April 4 Married Alice M. (Robertson) Stratton
1962 Assigned to Naval Reserve Office Training Corps Unit Stanford
1964 Master of Arts, International Relations, Stanford University Commissioned Lieutenant Commander Assigned as aide and executive assistant to the Deputy Direction, Joint Strategic Planning Staff, Strategic Air Command Headquarters, Offutt Air Force Base, Nebraska
1966 Joined Carrier Air Wing Nineteen, Attack Squadron One Ninety-two; deployed aboard the USS Ticonderoga to Tonkin Gulf, Southeast Asia
1967 January 5 Captured as a prisoner of war in North Vietnam within Fourth Allied POW Wing, Hanoi, North Vietnam
1969 May Commissioned Commander
1973 March 3 Released as part of Operation Homecoming
1973-1975 Executive Officer of Naval Plant Representative Office, Strategic Systems Project Office, Lockheed Missiles and Space Company
1975 Assigned Commanding Officer, Navy Recruiting District, New York, East Meadow Commissioned Captain
1977-1979 Commander, Recruiting Area Five, Great Lakes NTS, North Chicago, Illinois
1979-1981 Deputy for Operations, U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis, Maryland
1981-1986 Director, Naval Academy Preparatory School, NETC, Newport Rhode Island
1986 Retired from active duty
1988 Master of Social Work, Rhode Island College, School of Social Work
1989-1995 Chairman, Department of Veterans Affairs Advisory Committee on Prisoners of War
1997-2001 Contract counselor for sailors and families at Naval Submarine Base Kings Bay, Georgia and Naval Station Mayport, Florida
2001 Retired
Scope and Content of Collection
The Richard A. Stratton papers consist of correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, interview transcripts conference proceedings, printed matter, and audiovisual material relating to American prisoners of war and persons missing in action during the Vietnam War, and to the treatment of released prisoners in North Vietnam. The collection includes some papers of his wife, Alice M. Stratton, Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Navy for Force Support and Families (sometimes also referred to as "Personnel and Families"). The collection reflects Stratton's career both as a Navy pilot and social worker, as well as Alice Stratton's work for families of Naval officers and American POWs.
The Military Career File contains material relating to Richard Stratton's work in the Navy before and after the Vietnam War, including his Navy recruitment and courses he taught. The Alice M. Stratton File includes letters she received in response to a letter-writing campaign she conducted on behalf of Richard Stratton, as well as material relating to her work as deputy assistant secretary of the Navy after the Vietnam War. The Photographs series includes scenes of Stratton as a prisoner of war in North Vietnam's "Hanoi Hilton," as well as photographs by American photojournalist Lee Lockwood taken for Life magazine.
Throughout the collection, Richard A. Stratton is also referred to as "Dick" and "The Beak."
United States. Navy--Officers.; United States. Navy Department.; Prisoners of war.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Prisoners and prisons, North Vietnamese.
- Biographical File, 1952-2009
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains transcripts, news clippings, and other material about Richard Stratton. Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Academic transcripts, 1952-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Awards and certificates, 1956-2009 (Box-folder 1: 2-8, Box-folder 2: 1)
    Includes photographs from 1975 award ceremony for Silver Star, Legion of Merit, Bronze Star, and Navy Commendation Medal.
  - News clippings, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
    Contains news clippings about Richard Stratton.
  - Personnel files, 1955-1977 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Includes prints and negatives of Stratton's official Navy portrait photos.
- Correspondence, 1967-2010
  - General, 1972-2010
    - 1972 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 3: 1-3)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 3: 4-5)
    - 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1977-2010 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - POW camp letters, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - POW literature, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Contains correspondence, memorandum, bibliographies, and printed matter relating to literature by returned prisoners of war. Includes photocopies of book inscriptions addressed to Stratton from fellow prisoners of war.
  - Stockdale, James B., 1982 March - 1987 February (Box-folder 4: 3)
    Contains correspondence from Vice Admiral James B. Stockdale, a friend and fellow prisoner of war. Stockdale was also a historian and research fellow of the Hoover Institution.
- Speeches and Writings, 1964-2009, undated
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "POW Handwriting as an Indicator of Stress, 1967-1973,", undated (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - "First African Regional Conference of the International Labor Organization,", 1964 June (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Speaking engagements, 1973-1987 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Forum for Contemporary History, 1973 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Veteran's Day address, 1974 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - "Viet Notes U.S. Lack of Patience,", 1975 January (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Interview with Commander Richard A. Stratton by Captain Paul B. Ryan, 1975 September 28 (Box-folder 4: 10-12)
    Three typescript copies of Stratton's interview for the U.S. Naval Institute's Oral History program on the subject of "Experiences in the Vietnam War." One of the copies is annotated with corrections by Stratton. Also includes correspondence from Stratton to Captain Paul B. Ryan, a historian and research fellow at the Hoover Institution, and a memorandum from Ryan regarding its use.
  - "Turn on the Lights,", 1985 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Includes correspondence with editors of Marine Corps Gazette, Proceedings, and Reader's Digest.
  - "Nobody Asked Me, But...," Proceedings, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    Includes terms of publication contract with Proceedings and drafts of the article.
  - "Support the President in Getting the POWs Back from Vietnam,", 1986 March (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Tales of Southeast Asia, 2009 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    Includes a USB drive labelled "Richard Stratton, resource material for Tales of Southeast Asia and Prisoner at War."
- Speeches and Writings by Others, 1950-2008, undated
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Aerospace Speech Series, "Prisoner of War -- Missing in Action,", 1971 September (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Bailey, Rodney, "Sandcrab U.S.N.,", undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Benson, Jack and Daniel Bizzell, "Effects of Captivity and Commissioned/Enlisted Status on Short-Term and Long-Term Psychopathy in Former Prisoners of War,", undated (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Biderman, Albert D., "Dangers of Negative Patriotism" and "Necessary, Permissible, and Obligatory Discourse with Captor Personnel,", 1962-1963 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Blakely, Scott, "Prisoner at War: The Survival of Commander Richard A. Stratton,", 1978-1981 (Box-folder 5: 9-12)
    Includes typescript copy, correspondence, reviews, and memoranda relating to the publication.
  - Brayes, William, "The Road to Hill 10,", 1985 April (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Clifford, Rev. John W., "The First Step Is to Recognize It,", undated (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Coker, George, "P.W.,", 1974 October (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Colvin, John, "Hanoi Outside the Walls,", 1981 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Daugherty, William, "In the Shadow of the Ayatollah,", 2001 April (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Davis, W. J., "Hanoi-gate Marine,", 1986 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Dramesi, John, "Code of Honor,", 1974 November (Box-folder 6: 4-5)
  - Dunn, Joe, "The POW Chronicles,", 1983 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Lawes, Lewis E., "Prisons," Encyclopedia Americana, 1956 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Otten, Michael, "How Americans Look to Others,", undated (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Prickett, Lt. Col. W. F., "How Would You Do It,", 1951 January (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Scharff, Hanns Joachim, "Without Torture,", 1950 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Schein, Edgar H., "Roles--Not Rules--for the POW,", 1963 September (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Scurfield, Raymond, "Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder in Vietnam Veterans and Treatment of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Among Vietnam Veterans,", 1989 July (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Skelton, William Paul, "The Former American Prisoner of War,", 1993 (Box-folder 6: 13-14)
    Contains a printed copy of Skelton's lecture series and additional writings. Includes bibliography of lecture series presentation and a curriculum vitae.
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksander, excerpt of The First Circle and review by Stanton Evans, undated (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Stockdale, James B., 1978-1985 (Box-folder 6: 16, Box-folder 7: 1)
    Contains writings, articles, speeches, and clippings.
  - Webster, Steven D., "Maintaining Leadership Under Adverse Conditions,", 2008 October 17 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Military Career File, 1950-2013
  Contains correspondence, records, reports, and printed matter relating to Stratton's military career. Also includes information related to Stratton's biographical documentary, 2251 Days.
  - 2251 Days, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    Contains printed matter and correspondence relating to Stratton's biographical documentary produced by KQED.
  - Clearance records, 1955 December - 1975 January (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - "Code of Conduct" coursework, 1974-1987 (Box-folder 7: 5-7)
    Includes typescript speeches by others, memoranda regarding lectures, printed matter, handwritten notes regarding coursework, "The Military Spouse's 'Code of Conduct'" by Alice Stratton, and a transcript of an interview panel for the U.S. Naval Institute Professional Seminar Series featuring Stratton on the topic of the military "Code of Conduct."
  - Command history for the USS Ticonderoga, 1968, 2008 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - "Cultural Survival Guide: Southeast Asia," Intelligence Command Unit 202, 1976 June 15 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    A preliminary working draft prepared with the Center for Prisoner of War Studies, Naval Health Research Center.
  - Department of Defense, 1956-1970 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Endorsements for others, 1973-2013 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Family Liaison Action Group, 1980 March - December (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Finance records, 1956-1983 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Fitness reports, 1955 November - 1966 December (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Flight log books, 1955-1973 (Box-folder 8: 4-6)
  - Naval Academy, 1981 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Naval Chaplains School, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 8: 8-9)
    Contains speeches and writings, printed matter, reports, memoranda, and forms relating to coursework Stratton taught at the Naval Chaplains School. Includes "An Analysis of Factors Involved in Family Adjustments During Separations/Reunions: Opportunities for Ministry" by Paul Pyrch and Alice Stratton's speech for the Navy Chaplains School's senior course.
  - Naval War College, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    Contains correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter relating to Stratton's work as Director of the Academy of Preparatory School and coursework taught at the Naval War College. Also includes correspondence and articles written by James B. Stockdale.
  - Navy recruitment, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Officer effectiveness reports, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Operation Homecoming, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 9: 3-7)
    Contains interviews, correspondence, photographs, and printed matter regarding military orders, Oak Knoll Naval Hospital, rosters of returned prisoners of war, homecoming policy, message traffic, and gratuities for prisoners of war. Also see Photograph series for additional photos and slides of Oak Knoll Hospital.
  - Pilot flight records, 1957-1967 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Pilot log book, 1955-1963 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Repatriate Prisoner of War Program, undated (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Retirement record, 1985 October (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Roster, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Service records, 1955 May - 1983 October (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Training jacket booklet, 1955 (Box-folder 10: 6-7)
  - "U.S. Vulnerabilities as Portrayed in the East German Television Film, 'Pilots in Pajamas,'" Harley Preston, James Monroe, and Aldo Raffa, 1968 July 9 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950-1983 (Box-folder 10: 9)
    Includes material related to the military "Code of Conduct," rules of confinement, POW literature, and Stratton's political views in the 1950s. Also see Military Career File for additional material on "Code of Conduct."
- Alice M. Stratton File, 1955-1994
  Contains material related to Alice Stratton's work advocating for families of American POWs/MIAs and her position as a deputy assistant secretary to the Navy (DASN). Also includes personal documents, correspondence, speeches and writings, and printed matter relating to the Navy, POW/MIA advocacy groups, and the Stockholm Tribunal.
  - Biographical file, 1955-1994
    - Academic transcripts, 1955-1994 (Box-folder 10: 10)
    - Awards and certificates, 1971-1988 (Box-folder 10: 11, Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Bibliography, undated (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Biography, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 11: 3)
      Includes prints of Alice Stratton's official Navy portrait photo.
    - News clippings, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Diaries, 1985 August - 1989 March (Box 12)
    Contains 10 office diaries that Alice Stratton kept while she served as Deputy Assistance Secretary of the Navy (DASN) for Force Support and Families. This division is sometimes referred to as "Personnel and Families."
  - Correspondence, 1967-1972
    - Notification of POW status, 1967 (Box-folder 11: 5)
      Correspondence related to Richard Stratton's prisoner of war status.
    - Letters received from Hanoi, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 11: 6)
      Contains correspondence from visitors to Hanoi who relayed information and letters to and from Richard and Alice Stratton. Also see Stockholm Tribunal for additional correspondence, writings, and printed matter from visitors of Hanoi.
    - Ruefle, William J., 1969 August - 1970 September (Box-folder 11: 7)
      Contains correspondence, a photograph, roster of Joint Strategic Target Planning staff, and printed matter collected by Captain William J. Ruefle in his efforts to secure better treatment for American POWs. Also includes correspondence from his wife, Virginia Ruefle, to Alice Stratton.
    - Letter writing campaign, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 11: 8-9)
    - Letters received from Shoreland School, 1972 (Box-folder 11: 10)
      Contains letters of support for Richard Stratton from third graders of Shoreland School, addressed to Alice Stratton and family.
  - Speeches and writings, 1957-1991
    - "U.S. Prisoners of War and Missing in Action Personnel," presentation, undated (Box-folder 11: 11)
    - "Family Care Therapists at Northville State Hospital,", 1957 (Box-folder 11: 12)
    - "The Stress of Separation,", 1978 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Remarks for Department of Defense Family Service Center Program, 1985 November - 1987 October (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - Science and Engineering Apprenticeship Program Ribbon Cutting Ceremony, 1985 November 15 (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - "Volunteerism Can Be Career Enhancing," speech for Navy Wives Club, 1986 March 10 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Remarks to Civilian Personnel Directors, 1986 March 12 (Box-folder 13: 5)
    - Remarks to Ombudsmen University, 1986 April 5 (Box-folder 13: 6)
    - Remarks to John H. Russel Conference, 1986 April 22 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    - Remarks to the Integrated Warfare Course at Naval War College, 1986 May - September (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Remarks for POW Memorial Plaque and Garden Ceremony, 1986 July (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - Remarks to Navy Post Graduate School, 1986 July 8 (Box-folder 13: 10)
    - Remarks at National Naval Officer Association, 1986 July 11 (Box-folder 13: 11)
    - Remarks to Navy Social Workers Conference and Military Social Workers Dinner, 1986 September - 1989 June (Box-folder 13: 12)
    - Remarks to Marine Corps General's wives, 1986 September 22 (Box-folder 13: 13)
    - Coast Guard speech, 1986 December 16 (Box-folder 13: 14)
    - Speeches to Family Service Center Directors Conference, 1987 March 10 - April 9 (Box-folder 13: 15)
    - Remarks to Navy League National Convention, 1987 April 14 - 1988 June 6 (Box-folder 13: 16)
    - Remarks at Orlando Family Advocacy Conference, 1987 June 10 (Box-folder 13: 17)
    - Speech for Fleet and Force Master Chief spouses, 1987 October 13 (Box-folder 13: 18)
    - Remarks to AirPac Commanders Conference, 1987 October 20 (Box-folder 13: 19)
    - Speech for Fleet Reserve Association, 1988 March 16 (Box-folder 13: 20)
    - Speech for Military Spouses Business and Professional Association, 1988 October 3 (Box-folder 13: 21)
    - Remarks for Navy Education and Training Command, 1990 September 13 (Box-folder 13: 22)
    - Speech to the Retired Officers Association, 1991 April 6 (Box-folder 13: 23)
    - "War Time Stress for Parents of Warriors,", 1991 May (Box-folder 13: 24)
  - Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Navy file, 1977-1990
    Contains correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, and printed matter relating to Alice Stratton's work as Deputy Secretary of the Navy. Arranged alphabetically by subject. See also: Digital Files.
    - "An Annotated Bibliography: The Military Family,", 1981 (Box-folder 13: 25)
    - Appointment book, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 26)
    - Bibliography of Family Stress and Coping: The Military Family with Some Non-Military Family Comparisons, 1981 (Box-folder 13: 27)
    - Congressional transcript on child care, 1988 July 14 (Box-folder 13: 28)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 13: 29)
    - Dedication ceremony of Stratton Hall, 1990 February (Box-folder 13: 30)
    - Job description, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 31)
    - Memoranda, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 13: 32)
    - Navy-Marine Corps Family Support Conference, 1988 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
      Includes a photograph, printed matter, and remarks by Alice Stratton announcing Navy-Marine Corps Family Conference at CO/XO Conference, October 21, 1987.
    - Navy-Wide Family Awareness Conference, 1978 November (Box-folder 14: 3)
      Includes Alice Stratton's remarks for the USMC General Officers' Symposium, May 3, 1989, regarding outcomes of the Family Awareness Conference in 1978.
    - Photographs, 1989 (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - Printed matter, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - Reports, 1977-1988, undated
      Scope and contents note
      Includes reports received or written by Alice Stratton. Arranged alphabetically by title.
      - American Ex-Prisoners of War packets, 1987 November (Box-folder 14: 6-7)
        Includes packet 1: "Claim Information;"packet 2: "Stresses of Incarceration, After-Effects of Extreme Stress, Psychological, Neurological, Residual Nervous Conditions;" packet 3: "Arthritis, Alcoholism, Visual, Ulcer, Varicose Veins, Skin, Impotency, Brain Damage, Tuberculosis, etc.;" packet 4: "The After Effects of Incarceration: Part 1, the Heart, Arteries, and Veins: Part II, and Cancer;" packet 5: "What Every POW's Wife Should Know Before She's Your Widow;" packet 8: "The European Story;" packet 9: "The Korea Story;" and packet 10: "The Japanese Story."
      - As Parents Go, So Go the Children: The Adjustment and Development of Military Children, 1981 (Box-folder 14: 8)
      - Changing Families in a Changing Military System, Military Family Research Conference, 1977 (Box-folder 15: 1)
      - Description and Evaluation of an Information Outreach Program, Family Assistance Council Annapolis, undated (Box-folder 15: 2)
      - Final Evaluation Report Family Assistance Council Annapolis: Social Support and Personal Change, 1982 July (Box-folder 15: 3)
      - The Literature on Military Families, 1980: An Annotated Bibliography, 1980 August 1 (Box-folder 15: 4)
      - A Literature Review of the Military Family: Some Implications for Policy, undated (Box-folder 15: 5)
      - Longterm Effects of Parental Wartime Captivity on Children of POWs and MIA Servicemen, 1987 October (Box-folder 15: 6)
      - Proceedings: Conference on Follow-up Care for Returning Prisoners of War, 1985 March 12-14 (Box-folder 15: 7)
      - Proceedings of the Navy Family Service Center Workshop, 1982 March (Box-folder 15: 8)
      - Proceedings Report: National Council on Family Relations Pre-Conference Workshop "Quality of Family Life in the Military,", 1980 October 21 (Box-folder 15: 9)
      - Prolonged Separation: The Prisoner of War and His Family, undated (Box-folder 15: 10)
      - A Report on the Military Family Research Conference: Current Trends & Directions, 1977 September (Box-folder 15: 11)
      - The Role of the Leader in Taking Care of Our Families, 1986 April (Box-folder 15: 12)
      - Quality of Life Symposium: Report of Proceedings, 1988 (Box-folder 15: 13)
        Includes remarks by Alice Stratton at the Quality of Life Symposium, 1988 April 27.
    - Travel itineraries, 1986 January - July (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Visit to the USS Carl Vinson, undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Subject file, 1967-1974